William Wolcott Ellsworth Papers
Connecticut Historical Society
William Wolcott Ellsworth Papers.
1844 -- 1869
Connecticut Historical Society
Ellsworth, William Wolcott
Collection consists primarily of William Ellsworth's professional correspondence, created after Ellsworth's retirement from national and Connecticut political life, and his return to the practise of law.
0.75 linear feet(2 boxes)
Related Material
An index of catalog cards is available to aid access to this collection and material in other collections. Access is through writer, recipient and date. The card catalog is located in the Research Center reading room.
Microfilm copy available.
Biographical Sketch
William Ellsworth was born in Windsor, Connecticut on November 10, 1791 to Chief Justice Oliver Ellsworth. William and his twin brother, Henry Leavitt Ellsworth, prepared for college with Nathan Johnson. The brothers graduated from Yale College in 1810 and entered law training at Litchfield Law School.
Upon completing his formal law studies, William Ellsworth trained with Judge Thomas Scott Williams in Hartford. In 1813 he was admitted to the bar. On September 14 of that same year, he married Emily Webster, the eldest daughter of Noah Webster.
When Judge Williams went to Congress in 1817, Ellsworth was given charge of his mentor's law office. Ten years later, Ellsworth accepted a professorship of law at Trinity College in Hartford, a position he held until his death. In 1829, Ellsworth himself was elected to Congress. He served until 1834, resigning of his own accord. In 1838 he returned to politics as governor of Connecticut, a post he held for four years.
When Ellsworth had tired of politics, he returned to his law practice. In 1847 was made an associate judge of the state supreme court. He held this position until his 1861 retirement. William Ellsworth died in Hartford on January 15, 1868.
Scope and Content
Collection consists largely of letters written to William Ellsworth during the final twenty years of his law practice. Principal correspondents include: G. & C. Merriam, Chauncey Goodrich, Norman White, Henry Jones, W. G. Webster, and Henry Trowbridge.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically in a single series, Correspondence.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is open, but additional material is not expected.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Goodrich, Chauncey Allen, 1790-1860.; Jones, Henry, 1801-1878.; Merriam, Charles, 1806-1887.; Merriam, George Spring, 1843-1914.; Trowbridge, Henry.; Webster, W. G.
Corporate Names
G. & C. Merriam (Springfield, Mass.).
Genre Forms
Holographs; holographs, signed.
Contents:
- Series: Correspondence
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Henry White, W.G. Webster, Henry Jones, and Henry Trowbridge., 1844-1849 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as W.G. Webster, Henry Trowbridge, and Henry Jones., January - April 1850 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as W.G. Webster, Chauncey Goodrich, and Norman White., May 1850 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Chauncey Goodrich, Norman White, and Henry Jones., June 1850 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as George Cooledge, W.G. Webster, Henry Jones, and Henry Trowbridge., July - August 1850 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as W.G. Webster, Chauncey Goodrich, and Norman White., September - December 1850 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Henry Jones, W.G. Webster, R.S. Baldwin, and Henry Trowbridge., January - May 1851 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Henry Jones, Henry Trowbridge, W.G. Webster, Chauncey Goodrich, G. & C. Merriam, and Henry White., June - December 1851 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as W.G. Webster, George Morrison, and Chauncey Goodrich., January - February 1852 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Chauncey Goodrich, W.B. Smith, and W.G. Webster., March - May 1852 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as W.G. Webster, Henry Trowbridge, and Chauncey Goodrich., June - December 1852 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Henry Trowbridge, W.G. Webster, Henry Jones, and John Terhune., January 1853 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as George Cooledge, Henry Jones, and Chauncey Goodrich., February - September 1853 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Chauncey Goodrich, G. & C. Merriam, and W.G. Webster., October 1853 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Chauncey Goodrich, W.G. Webster, and George Cooledge., November - December 1853 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as W.G. Webster, W.C. Fowler, and Henry Trowbridge., January - March 1854 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Henry Trowbridge, G. & C. Merriam, and W.C. Fowler., April 1854 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Chauncey Goodrich, W.C. Fowler, and W.G. Webster., May 1854 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as W.G. Webster, G. & C. Merriam, and Chauncey Goodrich., June - October 1854 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Chauncey Goodrich, Henry Jones and W.G. Webster., November - December 1854 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Alfred Blackman and G. & C. Merriam., 1855 - March 1856 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as G. & C. Merriam., April - July 1856 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Chauncey Goodrich, G. & C. Merriam, and Norman White., August 1856 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as W.G. Webster, Norman White, and G. & C. Merriam., September 1-15, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Norman White, G. & C. Merriam, and Chauncey Goodrich., September 16-30, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Chauncey Goodrich and G. & C. Merriam., October 1856 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as G. & C. Merriam and Norman White., November - December 1856 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Chauncey Goodrich, G. & C. Merriam, and W.G. Webster., January - February 1857 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as Alfred Blackman, G. & C. Merriam, Chauncey Goodrich, and Charles Tracy., March - April 1857 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as G. & C. Merriam., May - July 1857 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as G. & C. Merriam and Charles Tracy; includes two drafts of an Act of Congress., August - December 1857 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as G. & C. Merriam., 1858 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as G. & C. Merriam., 1861 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence concerning such men as G. & C. Merriam, Chauncey Goodrich, Henry White., 1862-1869 (Box 2, Folder 12)